<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dysclosi[n]g of the canon of the popysh masse wyth a sermon annexed vnto it, of the famous clerke, of worthye memorye. D. Marten Luther.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1547</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07230</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106758</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842468</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842468</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7122</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07230)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7122)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 448:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dysclosi[n]g of the canon of the popysh masse wyth a sermon annexed vnto it, of the famous clerke, of worthye memorye. D. Marten Luther.</title>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Hans hitpricke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1547?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC, since copy as filmed lacks colophon.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on leaf B3r reads: A sermon made by the famous clerk of worthy memorye, Doctour Marten Luther, of the greate blasphemy agaynst God, which the Papystes daylie do vse, readyng thys Antechristian canon in theyr masses.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks all after leaf B3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mass --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7122:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7122:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The dyſcloſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the Canon of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſh Maſſe / wyth a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon annexed vnto it / of the famous Clerke / of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye memorye .D. Marten Luther.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Apocal. xviii.</bibl>
               <p>Come away from her my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that ye be not partakers i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her ſynnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye receyue not of her plages</p>
            </q>
            <p>All honour, prayſe and glorye be geuen onelye to God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7122:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7122:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>rom the beginnyng or at the fyrſt e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unce,<note place="margin">Geneſ. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> after the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acion (good chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reader) God in him ſelfe, foreſeing the ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of mannes harte,<note place="margin">John. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and how prone and readye it was vnto wyckednes, and howe oblyui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefytes that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of his lorde Gods han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,<note place="margin">Eſay. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> became not thankfull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hys myghtye God:<note place="margin">Roman. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> But va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed in the Imagynacions of hys frowarde fromake,<note place="margin">Ieremy. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and worſhipped the workmanſhip of the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of a caranous car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cas, ſubdued to all vanytie, &amp; forgat hys creatour: the why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch vngentelnes hath bene of al other vices,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> mooſt earneſtlye
<pb facs="tcp:7122:3"/>reprehended by the mouthe of God euen from the begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not onelie reprehended, but alſo wyth ſharpe threates and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynacions, of hys mooſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred woord,<note place="margin">Roma. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> appoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Beſydes that he gaue them vp to theyr har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes luſtes:<note place="margin">Sentere. <hi>28</hi>
               </note> and plaged them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſwearde, famyne and peſtyle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. Therfore (good chriſten re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) lyfte vp thyne eyes, ande beholde, the abhomynacyon of Idolatry,<note place="margin">.1. <hi>John.</hi>
2.</note> ſo ſhamefullie vſed in theſe dayes of our tyme:<note place="margin">.1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.</note> a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not onelie vſed, but with force and mayne fortefyed ande vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden,<note place="margin">Pſalm.
<hi>2.</hi>
               </note> wyth fyre and faggot, crudelytie and ſtrength: and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo ſore vpholden,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> that the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall woorde of God, is clerelie banyſſhed, exyled and put too
<pb facs="tcp:7122:3"/>bed. Howe ſayſte thou to thys deteſtable, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g all other, the mooſt ſhamefull maſe and gaſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſtocke,<note place="margin">Sapien. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> the wycked maſſe the vpſpryng of Sathan, the inuencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the deuel, the fayre frute of the Roomyſh raueni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Antechryſt,<note place="margin">Daniel. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> and the laderhous of all his ſhauen poſteritie?<note place="margin">Hieremy.
<hi>15.</hi>
               </note> Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>holde it, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d abhorre it: or elles take it for a warni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, God will abhorre the, and ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lake that burneth with fyre a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d brymſtone.<note place="margin">Apocal. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> Wherfore I harte lye beſech the, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all brotherly affeccyon,<note place="margin">Phill.
<hi>2.</hi>
               </note> marke in this lytell volume or fewe lynes, the tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le of the Dragon, of Gog and Magog, the waſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pore flocke of Chriſte,<note place="margin">Ezechiol. <hi>3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> the mayntey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of myſchefe, the ſtudyers of ſuperſticyon, the fortefyers <pb facs="tcp:7122:4"/>of the malignaunt Churche, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gylders of the triple Crowne:<note place="margin">Pſalm. <hi>26</hi>
               </note> and thou ſhalte playnelye par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue in an hondreth woordes,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> the ſhamefull legerdemayne &amp; craftie Iuggli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, that coſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtudy not of a fewe ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth yeres,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>13-</hi>
               </note> and the ſweate of manie browes: for the whyche bothe their pot and ſpitte, walke the merelier,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> vnto this howre. It is called the Canon of the myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheffat (of the Maſſe I woulde ſaye) that is to ſaye, the rule a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d order that they haue taken to fyniſh theyr ſlayne ſacrifyce; &amp; too brynge it to an ende. But what turmoyling, ſtruggling, wraſtlinge,<note place="margin">Luke.
<hi>11.</hi>
               </note> quid pro quo, with my wayes is beſt, hold thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de fro my throte, ther was till they had broughte it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhapen
<pb facs="tcp:7122:4"/>forme, that it is nowe in: Polidorus Virgilius doth playnelye manifeſt.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>5.</hi> Cap
<hi>10.</hi>
               </note> Wheru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to alſo y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt a ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nexed, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> famous Clerke, &amp; diſcloſer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes Iuggli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g box, &amp; of wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy memorye. D. Marte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Reade it (I pray y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>) w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And conferre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Idolatries of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old time, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the abhominable Idolatry in our tyme, after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſt, the pure &amp; true light: a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt ſe it farre paſſe.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Oh moſt mightie father, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der loue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou bareſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl world,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> in that thou delyueredſt thyn onelye and ſwete ſonne Ieſus Chryſte,<note place="margin">Hebr.
<hi>10</hi>
               </note> that holye and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſacryfice,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> for the lyfe of the whole world. Haue mercy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs &amp; deliuer vs, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſnares <pb facs="tcp:7122:5"/>of Sathan, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d from the deue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſh yoke of this deteſtable I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrye: and open the eyes of oure Magyſtrates,<note place="margin">Pſalm. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> that they may proſperouſly,<note place="margin">Coloſſ.
<hi>4.</hi>
               </note> fortefie thy bleſſed woorde (as theye haue bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne gracyouſlie) and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face the bloudye kyngdome of Antechryſte. And ſende the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munaltie obedient ſtomackes &amp; hartes,<note place="margin">Apocal. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> to fortefye their Pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces quarell,<note place="margin">Roma. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> in all godlynes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ryght. And that all chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes,<note place="margin">Timoth. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> maye accorde in peace &amp; vnytie, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo to be incorporate in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myſticall bodye of God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghtye,<note place="margin">Roma.
<hi>12.</hi>
               </note> whoſe head is chryſt Ieſus. To whome I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the increaſe of his knowledge, Amen.</p>
            <p>Reade, and then Iudge.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:7122:5"/>
            <head>The dyſcloſynge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>e hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blie pray &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fay<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> accept &amp; bleſſe theſe gifts theſe rewardes,<note place="margin">here the Pr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eeſt kiſſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aulter, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>n maketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Croſſes.</note> th<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſe holy vntaſted ſacrifices, Ch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>efely which we offer vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for thy holy catholyke churche, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou myghteſt voucheſafe too pacify, kepe, ſet togyther &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uern it through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl world, w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t our pope (&amp; name hym) and our byſſhop (named) a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d our kyng (named) a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all faithfull me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and louers of the catholike a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d apoſtolike faith. Remembre lord thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and women (he nameth whom he will) and all that ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de here about,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> here he pr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aieth for the lyui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th no word, but thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keth them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he praieth for.</note> whoſe fayth and deuocion is knowen to the, for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we offer, or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues offer <pb facs="tcp:7122:6"/>this ſacrifice of prayſe, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and theyrs, for redempcion of their ſoules, for hope of theyre owne health and proſperitie: &amp; paye theyr vowes to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, lyuinge and true God: ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng parte, and worſhyppyng the remembraunce ſpeciallye, of the gloryous a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d perpetuall vyrgin Mary, mother of oure God and lorde Ieſus Chryſte. Yea, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of thy bleſſed Apoſtles and Martyrs alſo, as Peter, Paule, Andrew, Iames, Iohn Thomas, Iams, Phillip, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholome, Mathye, Symon a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Iude, Lyne, Clete, Clemente, Sixt, Cornele, Cipryan, Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens, Gryſogon, Iohn &amp; Paul, Coſmas and damian, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of all thy Sayntes, through whoſe merytes and prayers, graunt <pb facs="tcp:7122:6"/>thou that we may i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges be defended by the helpe of thy protection, by the ſame Chryſt oure lorde. Amen</p>
            <p>We beſeche the therfore, (O lorde) to bee pacifyed, and too accept thys oblacyon.<note n="3" place="margin">here he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kethe on the hoſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great deuocion.</note> and too bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den dutie, yea &amp; of thy hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhold alſo, and to dyſpoſe oure dayes, in thy peace, and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we maye be delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eternall dampnacion, and bee no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flocke of thyn elect throgh Chriſt our lord, Amen.</p>
            <p>Whych oblacion.<note n="4" place="margin">here he muſt loke on it agayne.</note> vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe thou God almyghty, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke throughly (we beſech y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>) bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<note n="5" place="margin">her he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.
<hi>5.</hi> Croſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes.</note> the appointed, ratefyed &amp; acceptable,<note place="margin">Here he ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vp and Ioyneth his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wepeth his fingers lifteth vppe hys ſacrifice and ſaith. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be made to vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body &amp; bloude of thy de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ieſus Chriſte.
<hi>6.</hi> who y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day befor he ſuffred toke bred i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his holy &amp; worſhipfull ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des <pb facs="tcp:7122:7"/>and lifted vp hys eyes into he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,<note n="7" place="margin">he caſteth vp his eyes.</note> to the, God hys father almyghtie, he gaue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to the, and bleſſed it, brake it and gaue it to his dyſciples, ſayi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, take &amp; eate of this all, for thys is my bodye.<note n="8" place="margin">he maketh obeyſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d then lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it vp o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his head</note>
            </p>
            <p>In like ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner after ſupper was done, he tooke this noble cuppe in his holy and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full handes, and gaue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to the,<note n="9" place="margin">he maketh curteſye.</note> a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bleſſed.<note n="10" place="margin">he Croſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ones.</note> 10. &amp; gaue hys dyſciples, ſaying, take ye, and dri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke of it all,<note n="11" place="margin">he lifteth the Chalyce vp a lytle.</note> for thys is the Cuppe of my bloude of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> newe Teſtament, the miſtery of fayth, which ſhalbe ſhed for you and for manny, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſion of ſynnes.<note n="12" place="margin">he lifteth vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chalice ouer his head</note> As often as euer ye do thys, ye ſhall do it in the remembraunce of me. Wherby both we thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes
<pb facs="tcp:7122:7"/>remembre Lorde, and ſo doo thy holye people reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre the ſame Chryſt thy ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne our lord God: as well his bleſſed paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as his reſurrection, yea, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo his glorious aſcencion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen: and offer to thy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Maieſtie, of thy preſentes and gyftes, a pure.<note n="13" place="margin">he croſſeth hys geare. <hi>5.</hi> tymes.</note> ſacrifice a holy ſacrifyce, an vnſpotted ſacrifice: the holye breade of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall lyfe, and the Cuppe of euer laſtyng ſaluacyon. Ouer whych, vouchſafe thou to loke wythe a mercyfull and cleare countenaunce, and accept it, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as thou dydeſt vouchſafe too accepte the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of thy ſeruaunte Iuſte Abell: ande y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacryfyce of oure hyghe father Abraham and that whych thy hyghe preeſt Melchiſedech of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred <pb facs="tcp:7122:8"/>a holy ſacrifice, an vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted hoſte. We humbly deſyre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almighty God, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>naund theſe thinges to be borne, by the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of thy holy Angell, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to thy Aulter aboue, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of thy Godly Maieſtie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as many of vs, as haue taken parte of this Aulter, and haue receyued the holy halowed body and bloud of thy ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, may be replenyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.<note n="14" place="margin">he Croſſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth his face.</note> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly bleſſyng and grace, thorough the ſame Chryſte oure lorde Amen</p>
            <p>Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre abſo lorde thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, men. N. &amp; wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. N. which are gone before vs.<note n="15" place="margin">he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad &amp; ſpeketh neuer a wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, butt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he lifte</note> with the ſigne of faythe, and ſtepe in the ſtepe of peace, we beſech y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord to pardonne them and all that reſt in Chriſte, and geue them a place of refreſſhi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, light and <pb facs="tcp:7122:8"/>reſt: through the ſame Chryſte our lorde, Amen.</p>
            <p>To vs thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntes alſo,<note place="margin">he knocketh hym ſelfe on the breſt.</note> 
               <hi>16</hi> hopi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g on the multitude of thy mercies: vouchſafe to geue ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me parte a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d felouſhippe, with thy holye Apoſtles &amp; Martirs, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iohn, Stephen, Mathias, Barnabas, Ignacius, Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Marcelline, Peter, Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, Perpetua Agatha, Lucie, Agnes, Cecilye, Anaſtaſeus: &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all thy ſeints amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>y we beſech y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> admitt vs, not eſtemi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g our deſerui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grant of thy pardon, throughe Chriſte our lord,<note n="17" place="margin">Amen is not ſpoken here.</note> By whome O lord all theſe good thinges y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> allwayſe createſt ſanctyfieſt quickeneſt bleſſeſt ande geueſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tobs.<note n="18" place="margin">he bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyce w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>5</hi> cro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſſes.</note> By hym and wyth hym &amp; in hym, be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God the
<pb facs="tcp:7122:9"/>father almyghty, in the vnytie of the holy gooſt, all honour a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d glorye.<note n="19" place="margin">he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth alowd</note> for euer woorlde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende,<note n="20" place="margin">y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Clerke a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwereth.</note> Amen. We beyng warned by wholſome precep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ande infourmed by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucion of God, dare boldely ſaye.<note n="21" place="margin">he hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vp hys handes.</note> Our father whych art in heauen, holowed be thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Thy kyngdom come. Thy wyll be done in earth, as it is in heauen. Gyue vs thys daye oure daylie bread. And forgy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vs our treſpaſſe, as we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that treſpaſſe agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt vs. And lett vs not be led into tentacion.<note n="22" place="margin">the Cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke ſayth.</note> But delyuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me euell,<note n="23" place="margin">the preeſt ſaith ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye.</note> Amen. Dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs Lorde, we beſeche the, from all euelles paſt, preſent &amp; for too come, and by the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the bleſſed and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <pb facs="tcp:7122:9"/>perpetuall virgin Marye the mother of God, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtles, Peter and Paule and Andrew, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all thy Sayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.<note n="24" place="margin">He kiſſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th the paten, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> putteth it to his right eye, then to his lyft eye, then he croſſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth his crou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e and layeth it dou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e againe.</note> Be mercifull and gyue peace in our dayes, that we (be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng holpen, by the helpe of thy mercy) maye be alwayes both free from ſynne, and ſafe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me all trouble.<note n="25" place="margin">He breke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th the Hoſte in iii. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes firſt i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ii. ſayeng.</note> by the ſame our lorde Ieſus Chriſt thy ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne.<note n="26" place="margin">Here he maketh it iii. peeces.</note> whych w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lyueth and reyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, in the vnytie of the holye ghooſte.<note n="27" place="margin">He ſpek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth alowde.</note> for euer ande euer,<note n="28" place="margin">The clerk ſayth.</note> Amen. The peace of.<note n="29" place="margin">He croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice. iii. times w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one pece of the Hoſte.</note> the lord he euer wyth you. O la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be of God, which takeſt away the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, haue mercy on vs. O la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be of god whych takeſt away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of the woord, haue mercy on vs. O lambe of God which takeſt away the ſinne of <pb facs="tcp:7122:10"/>the world, geue vs peace.<note n="30" place="margin">He croſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the hoſt a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d then put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chalyce</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thys holye mengli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the body &amp; bloud of our Lord Ieſus Chryſt be to me &amp; to all that receaue it, ſaluacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mynde and body, and a heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thfull preparacyon to deſerue ande receaue euerlaſting lyfe, trough y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Chryſt our lord Amen.</p>
            <p>O holy lord, father almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty eternall God, graunt me to receaue this holy body &amp; blod of thy ſonne our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt ſo worthily: that I may deſerue by it to receaue remyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all my ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, &amp; to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy holy ſpyrit &amp; to haue thy peace: for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art god alone &amp; ther is none other but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>, whoſe ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pery laſteth gloryous, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ende for euer <pb facs="tcp:7122:10"/>&amp; euer Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note n="32" place="margin">he kiſſeth the paxe.</note> Peace be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of God.<note n="33" place="margin">The clerk ſayth.</note> &amp; to thy ſpyrite</p>
            <p>O God the father, fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayne a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning of all goodnes, wh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch by mercye we reſt ledde, and wouldeſt that thyne onelye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne, ſhoulde comme doune, too the loweſte partes of the woorlde, and take fleſh, whych I vnworthy holde here in my ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des.<note n="34" place="margin">He kne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth doune to the Hoſte.</note> I worſhip the, I glorify y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, yea w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of my hart I prayſe the: &amp; beſech the, that thoue forſake not vs thy ſeruauntes, butt forgyue oure ſynnes, ſo that we maye bee able, too ſerue the, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye lyuynge and trewe GOD, wyth a pure harte and a chaſte boddye. Thoroughe the ſame Ieſus Chryſt our lorde, Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <pb facs="tcp:7122:11"/>Let the obſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce pleaſe the,<note n="35" place="margin">After th<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>is Colet, he maketh a cr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oſſe on the Aulter, kiſſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth it &amp; put<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth of hys vpper veſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re.</note> O holy tryny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and graunt that thys ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, whych I vnworthy haue offred to the eyes of thy Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, may be acceptable to the: &amp; propiciatorie too me and to all them that I haue offred it for, through thy mercy, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch liueſt and reigneſt GOD, woorlde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>oute ende Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7122:11"/>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:7122:11"/>
            <head>A ſermon ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de by the famous Clerk of worthy memorye, Doctour Marten Luther, of the greate blaſphemy agaynſt God, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch the Papyſtes daylie do vſe, readyng thys Antechriſtian Canon in theyr Maſſes</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>efore we take on, to vew or ſuruey that horrible abhomyna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Idolatry agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſte God, of the mooſte curſed Canon (whych the ſluggiſh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſtes call the maſſe) in whych they wyth cruell mouth dayly beſlauer the hygh Maieſtye of God: we thynk it beſt, that we <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
